<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Sébastien Lerique - Tooling</title><link href="//slvh.fr/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//slvh.fr/feeds/tooling.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//slvh.fr/</id><updated>2017-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Tools of the Trade</title><link href="//slvh.fr/posts/2017-02-01-tools-of-the-trade/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sébastien Lerique</name></author><id>tag:slvh.fr,2017-02-01:/posts/2017-02-01-tools-of-the-trade/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you use your computer daily, tooling up can change your&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Tools? Why dear god,&amp;nbsp;why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an avid fan of the enactive approach to cognitive science, I deeply agree with Gregory Bateson&amp;#8217;s idea that the blind person&amp;#8217;s stick is part of their body and general sensorimotor apparatus (I&amp;#8217;m not alone in&amp;nbsp;this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes for one&amp;#8217;s everyday work tool, and in my case that&amp;#8217;s the personal computer.
One can go a long way with that principle, and prime examples are Bret Victor&amp;#8217;s talks &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/115154289"&gt;The Humane Representation of Thought&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/97903574"&gt;Seeing Spaces&lt;/a&gt;, setting out wonderful visions of how computerised tools could (will?) empower us in thought and creativity, turning e.g. the reflexive craft of programming into dynamic performance (also watch &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/71278954"&gt;The Future of Programming&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;#8217;re into&amp;nbsp;this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s also more modest achievements in modelling one&amp;#8217;s everyday interactions, of course. One of those, I think, is proper everyday tooling.
So since I have wondered many times about ways to transform my everyday thinking, with various attempts at practices to grow the fleeting ideas and wonderful imaginative feelings one can have throughout the course of a day;
since I have been asking myself what stuff people develop to cope with the ephemerality of thought, here is my current list of tools and&amp;nbsp;tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I can come across something similar in the future published by other people, or even spark some conversation! (In some slightly more developed form than a &lt;code&gt;dotfiles&lt;/code&gt; repository.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, rather&amp;nbsp;bluntly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Desktop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.archlinux.org/"&gt;ArchLinux&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href="https://i3wm.org/"&gt;i3&lt;/a&gt; as window manager, and Gnome Terminal with &lt;a href="https://fishshell.com/"&gt;fish shell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apps/programs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://neovim.io/"&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt; for file editing, Firefox with the &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/tab-tree/"&gt;Tab Tree&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/vimfx/"&gt;VimFx&lt;/a&gt; extensions (and Zotero and other standard stuff) for browsing, &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; for&amp;nbsp;blogging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; with Python&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://scipy.org/"&gt;scientific ecosystem&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://elm-lang.org/"&gt;Elm&lt;/a&gt;, and git. Occasionally &lt;a href="http://julialang.org/"&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully a lot more of, soon, &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tracking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Gnote"&gt;Gnote&lt;/a&gt; for permanent notes and scratchpads, &lt;a href="http://rednotebook.sourceforge.net/"&gt;RedNotebook&lt;/a&gt; for all dated notes, and &lt;a href="http://projecthamster.org/"&gt;Hamster&lt;/a&gt; to track time spent on tasks and keep a good overview of work&amp;nbsp;hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interface and&amp;nbsp;incentives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dvorak keyboard layout. &lt;a href="http://www.workrave.org/"&gt;Workrave&lt;/a&gt; to push me to take regular breaks so I don&amp;#8217;t go blind because of too much screen, and &lt;a href="http://jonls.dk/redshift/"&gt;RedShift&lt;/a&gt; so that said screen stays comfortable at all hours of the day and&amp;nbsp;night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There should be an up-to-date version of this list in the &lt;a href="/tools/"&gt;Tools&lt;/a&gt; page from now&amp;nbsp;on!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tooling"></category><category term="layout"></category><category term="tooling"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning Dvorak</title><link href="//slvh.fr/posts/2017-01-25-learning-dvorak/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sébastien Lerique</name></author><id>tag:slvh.fr,2017-01-25:/posts/2017-01-25-learning-dvorak/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I decided to learn Dvorak. It went pretty&amp;nbsp;well!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I decided I wanted to learn Dvorak. It&amp;#8217;s a keyboard layout which, unlike traditional Qwerty/Qwertz/Azerty layouts, is optimised to reduce the distance your fingers travel when typing in English. The Qwerty layout, instead, was invented for the mechanical typewriter and is optimised so that two adjacent hammers would only very rarely be typed one directly after the other. That effectively translates to a lot more movement for your fingers than is necessary with software&amp;nbsp;today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a month and a half to be productive, practising about 20 minutes a day on &lt;a href="https://learn.dvorak.nl/"&gt;learn.dvorak.nl&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s a lot shorter than I expected! I haven&amp;#8217;t reached my Qwerty speed yet, but I&amp;#8217;m comfortably using my computer for work in Dvorak all day long, with emails, vim, and i3, meaning a lot of blind shortcuts have become automatic. Not bad, I&amp;nbsp;feel..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing the training, and deciding to try the layout for real stuff, the first few programming sessions quickly led to intense frustration and wanting to smash the computer to pieces. Aaaaaargh!!! Okay. Change layout back to Qwerty. Goodness I can type&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intriguing experience, how unconscious the typing process can become, and how painful it is when it&amp;#8217;s taken away. Even more surprising, after only 4-5 days of trying this and stopping whenever I got frustrated, it became actually comfortable to use Dvorak. I&amp;#8217;m amazed at how fast this&amp;nbsp;goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next step: learning Bépo, the Dvorak-inspired layout for&amp;nbsp;French.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tooling"></category><category term="dvorak"></category><category term="layout"></category><category term="tooling"></category></entry></feed>